<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://internetequity.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://internetequity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-26T21:35:58+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Internet Innovation Initiative</title><subtitle>Developing tools and techniques for measuring Internet performance and connectivity at the University of Chicago </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mapping Internet Quality Across America with the Internet Innovation Initiative</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/mapping-internet-quality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping Internet Quality Across America with the Internet Innovation Initiative"/><published>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/mapping-internet-quality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/mapping-internet-quality/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/mapping-screenshot-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/mapping-screenshot-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/mapping-screenshot-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/mapping-screenshot.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>If you follow our research, you know that broadband measurement is at the heart of our project. The Internet Innovation Initiative’s core insight is leveraging advances in edge computing and hardware to improve broadband measurement for research and policy while reducing the costs and complexity of managing edge deployments. Our work over the last two years has helped support multiple efforts by researchers and policymakers to collect robust broadband performance data needed for effective analysis and decision-making.</p> <p>The recent work of three students from the University of Chicago Data Science Institute’s Data Science Clinic further emphasizes the policy issues facing universal broadband access in the United States. The video summarizing their work and research is an excellent resource for understanding the complexities of broadband policy in the United States. It also surfaces the need for better broadband data in general to improve our methods of identifying where better infrastructure is needed the most.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="broadband"/><category term="policy"/><category term="measurement"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Students examine the complexities of broadband policy in the United States.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Case Study: Collaboration with Greater Englewood Chamber of Commerce to Address Digital Inequity</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/englewood-case-study/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Case Study: Collaboration with Greater Englewood Chamber of Commerce to Address Digital Inequity"/><published>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/englewood-case-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/englewood-case-study/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/englewood-screenshot-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/englewood-screenshot-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/englewood-screenshot-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/englewood-screenshot.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="lighting-up-englewood-how-data-and-community-collaboration-are-tackling-the-digital-divide">Lighting Up Englewood: How Data and Community Collaboration are Tackling the Digital Divide</h2> <p>In a world that runs on connectivity, reliable internet access is not a luxury—it’s a lifeline. For the vibrant community of Englewood on Chicago’s South Side, this lifeline has remained just out of reach, despite fiber optic cables lying dormant beneath their streets. This is the story of how the Internet Innovation Initiative, in partnership with the Greater Englewood Chamber of Commerce (GECC), is working to change that.</p> <p>Our journey in Englewood began over 18 months ago when we met the dynamic Executive Director of the GECC, Felicia Statton-Young. Through our conversations, we uncovered a frustrating paradox: Englewood had the physical infrastructure for high-speed internet, yet major service providers were unwilling to “light up” this dark fiber without guaranteed, full-price subscriptions from residents—a significant barrier for many in the community.</p> <p>This digital inequity directly impacts economic growth, educational opportunities, and the overall well-being of the neighborhood. We knew that to advocate for change, the community needed more than just stories; they needed data.</p> <h2 id="from-conversation-to-action">From Conversation to Action</h2> <p>To truly understand the challenges faced by local businesses, our team became a regular presence at GECC meetings. We listened to the concerns of small business owners, delivered a presentation on the power of internet equity, and began to formulate a plan.</p> <p>The first step was to quantify the problem. Anecdotes about slow speeds and unreliable connections needed to be backed by hard evidence. To achieve this, we organized a giveaway of speedtester devices specifically for Englewood’s small business owners where we gave out over a dozen devices for measurement.</p> <p>This is where our infrastructure became a critical tool for change. Our role in this initiative is to:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Measure Reality:</strong> Provide easy-to-use speedtester devices that capture the real-time quality of existing internet services.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Gather Evidence:</strong> Remotely manage the deployed devices and collect performance data, building a detailed, localized map of internet quality.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Empower Advocacy:</strong> Analyze the collected data to create a powerful evidence-based case for better service.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="the-road-ahead">The Road Ahead</h2> <p>Our work in Englewood is an ongoing commitment. As we continue our partnership with the GECC, we are focused on expanding the deployment of devices to build an even more comprehensive picture of the area’s internet landscape. The data we collect will be the foundation of a sustained advocacy campaign, empowering community partners to demand the reliable, high-speed infrastructure they deserve.</p> <p>This initiative in Englewood is a testament to how technology, when guided by community engagement, can illuminate hidden inequities and drive meaningful change. By providing tangible data and unwavering support, we are helping to empower communities to build the connected, thriving future they envision.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="case-study"/><category term="community"/><category term="chicago"/><category term="digital-divide"/><category term="case-study"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How community partnerships and data collection can illuminate hidden inequities and catalyze meaningful change.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Case Study: IPv4 vs. IPv6 Internet Speed Analysis</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/ipv4-vs-ipv6-analysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Case Study: IPv4 vs. IPv6 Internet Speed Analysis"/><published>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/ipv4-vs-ipv6-analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2024/ipv4-vs-ipv6-analysis/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This blog post is by one of our project collaborators, Amanda Hsu, a researcher at Georgia Institute of Technology who is using our platform to conduct research.</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/ipv6-stats-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/ipv6-stats-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/ipv6-stats-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/ipv6-stats.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Google recently reports over 47% of its users connect over IPv6, a number that has been steadily increasing in the past 20 years. Source: https://www.google.com/intl/en/ipv6/statistics.html </div> <p>Every device connected to the Internet, whether it’s your computer, phone, or refrigerator, has an IP address. IP addresses are the Internet’s mailing system; they tell routers where to send their packets and allow machines to connect. However, as the Internet has evolved, IP addressing has become challenging.</p> <p>At the Internet’s conception, IPv4 was the only type of IP address. IPv4 addresses have 32 bits, which means that there are 2³² (over 4 billion) total addresses. While that may seem like a lot, the Internet ran out of these addresses in 2019 [3]. Fortunately, this was anticipated, and IPv6 addressing was created long beforehand. IPv6 addresses have 128 bits, which means there are 2¹²⁸ (over 340 trillion trillion trillion) unique addresses. Now, with IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, it is unlikely the Internet will ever run out.</p> <p>Since the Internet started approaching IPv4 exhaustion, IPv6 deployment has increased exponentially over the past 20 years. This has allowed the Internet to continue expanding. However, it is now a hybrid of IPv4, IPv6, and dual-stack (both IPv4 and IPv6) networks. Household Internet connections are no different, with some residences using IPv4, IPv6, or both, depending on their service provider. Despite both being IP protocols, IPv4 and IPv6 cannot connect by default, often operate over different Internet paths, may be processed differently by router hardware, and, therefore, experience different levels of loss and latency.</p> <p>Despite both being IP protocols, IPv4 and IPv6 cannot communicate directly with each other without the use of transition technologies to bridge the gap. Homes can have access to IPv4, IPv6, or both. In this project, we focus on residences with both IPv4 and IPv6.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/ipv4-ipv6-comparison-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/ipv4-ipv6-comparison-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/ipv4-ipv6-comparison-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/ipv4-ipv6-comparison.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Despite this, most prior work that measures residential Internet speed does not account for this important factor. Anecdotally, many Internet users have noticed a difference between their IPv4 and IPv6 speeds [1,2]. However, there has yet to be a large-scale study that empirically measures the differences in speed tests on IPv4 and IPv6.</p> <p>In this project, we seek to understand how Internet speed varies between IPv4 and IPv6 and why. We perform speed tests over IPv4 and IPv6 using the Internet Innovation Initiative platform and compare the results over time. We perform these speed tests one after another to capture similar conditions. Then, we directly compare the results and correlate the speed test conditions to the results.</p> <p>In this project, we specifically seek to answer the following research questions:</p> <ul> <li>How does using IPv4 or IPv6 affect a user’s Internet speed?</li> <li>How do standard speed tests, such as Ookla and NDT7, change with using IPv4 and IPv6?</li> <li>Why do measured speeds vary over IPv4 and IPv6? Do the paths introduce bottlenecks? Or do routers process IPv4 and IPv6 packets at different speeds?</li> </ul> <p>With the results of this project, we hope to encourage future research to use IPv4 and IPv6 as a factor in Internet speed analysis. Large-scale Internet speed measurements are often used to inform policies, such as those by the FCC [4] on broadband speed coverage. With an in-depth understanding of broadband coverage, researchers and policy-makers alike can identify communities with low availability and provide them with resources for better Internet access. By understanding the effect of IPv4 and IPv6, we hope broadband coverage analysis will be more accurate and impactful.</p> <p>Early results of our measurements indicate that IPv4 and IPv6 degrade in speed under different conditions. For example, at times when IPv4 speed is slower, IPv6 speed is not necessarily also affected. Moreover, the conditions that these speeds degrade are correlated with the Internet Service Provider.</p> <p>We look forward to understanding these circumstances in more depth throughout this project.</p> <p><strong>References:</strong></p> <p>[1] https://community.netgear.com/t5/Nighthawk-Wi-Fi-5-AC-Routers/Why-IPv6-can-be-slower-than-IPv4/td-p/2231369</p> <p>[2] https://community.ui.com/questions/High-load-on-USG-after-enabling-IPv6/964b80ce-325a-4cfa-b25a-cbecd4afcfaf</p> <p>[3] https://www.ripe.net/manage-ips-and-asns/ipv4/ipv4-run-out/</p> <p>[4] https://www.fcc.gov/BroadbandData</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="case-study"/><category term="ipv4"/><category term="ipv6"/><category term="measurement"/><category term="case-study"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Examining how Internet speed differs between IPv4 and IPv6 protocols.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Your WiFi Limiting Your Home Internet Performance?</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/wifi-limiting-performance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Your WiFi Limiting Your Home Internet Performance?"/><published>2022-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/wifi-limiting-performance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/wifi-limiting-performance/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Antonia Sanhueza and Marc Richardson contributed to the drafting and analysis of this data story. Special thanks to Tarun Mangla, Kyle MacMillan, Nicole Marwell, and Nick Feamster for their feedback. To download the data used in this analysis, visit our GitHub data repository (netrics-data).</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1314037715-e1665782372806-1440x580-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1314037715-e1665782372806-1440x580-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1314037715-e1665782372806-1440x580-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1314037715-e1665782372806-1440x580.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>If you’re frustrated with the speed of your home Internet, what can you do to improve it? Perhaps, after experiencing lag during a video call with your family, you entertained switching service providers or upgrading your service to an Ultra-Fast Gigabit connection. Surely a connection that fast will save you from the headache of slow Internet for the rest of your online life, right? Maybe not. Before making the leap to a new provider or absorbing the often difficult-to-swallow costs of a high-speed service plan, you might want to consider another culprit of slow Internet: your WiFi connection.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/wifi-connection-diagram7.svg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/wifi-connection-diagram7.svg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: WiFi Connection and Wired (Access) Connection in a Household </div> <p>Typically, when someone connects to the Internet, they first connect to a WiFi router in their home via a wireless network, which then connects them through a wired network to the rest of the Internet, as shown in Figure 1. A household’s WiFi connection might perform differently than the wired (or access) connection. WiFi connection performance is determined by factors independent of your access connection, while the access connection performance is (primarily) determined by the specific service contract you purchase from a service provider (ISP). WiFi bottlenecks occur when the speed of your WiFi connection (the WiFi speed) is worse than the speed of the access connection (the access speed).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/wifi-data-story-household-bottlenecks1.svg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/wifi-data-story-household-bottlenecks1.svg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: Comparing a Household with Bottlenecks to a Household Without Bottlenecks </div> <p>To illustrate, consider Figure 2, which shows WiFi speeds (yellow line) and access speeds (red line) from November 2021 to April 2022 for two households in Chicago. The household on the left has WiFi speeds below access speeds. WiFi is a bottleneck 100 percent of the time for this household. Conversely, the household on the right has WiFi speed that almost always exceeds access speed and rarely bottlenecks Internet performance. Note that the household with WiFi bottlenecks is paying for Internet service with high access speeds (~700 Mbps) whereas the household with no bottlenecks is paying for low access speeds (~50 Mbps). As we show in the analysis below, the prevalence of WiFi bottlenecks is highly correlated with the access speed that a household purchases.</p> <p>Why should you care about WiFi bottlenecks? Because they can significantly affect your online experience. Your access connection might support very high speeds, but if your WiFi connection is poor, you are not going to experience good Internet performance. WiFi bottlenecks also have important implications for policies aiming to improve Internet performance in a community. Such policies must include investments directed toward assessing and improving the WiFi equipment that households use to access the Internet.</p> <p>In the analysis below, we explore how often WiFi bottlenecks occur and the relative difference between WiFi speeds and access speeds using data collected from households in Chicago.</p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>In April 2021, a Pew Research Center survey found that “roughly half of [U.S.] broadband users report[ed] that they often (12%) or sometimes (37%) experienced problems with the speed, reliability or quality of their high-speed Internet connections at home” and that “29% of broadband users did something to improve the speed, reliability or quality of their [home Internet] since the beginning of the pandemic”. The survey highlights that many people experience problems with their Internet performance and want to improve it. But, deciding how best to improve home Internet performance first requires answering an important question: Where do bottlenecks of home Internet performance arise?</p> <p>To evaluate performance bottlenecks at the household level, we examine speed test data from our Netrics devices. We used Measurement Lab’s Network Diagnostic Tool (NDT7) to measure the download speeds of both the WiFi and access connections of 47 households in Chicago from October 2021 to September 2022. We then compare each household’s WiFi speed to its access speed over time and analyze the number of times and by how much WiFi speed fell below access speed.</p> <h2 id="how-common-are-wifi-bottlenecks">How Common Are WiFi Bottlenecks?</h2> <p>The first question we explore with the data is how common WiFi bottlenecks are across the households in our sample. To calculate the prevalence of bottlenecks for each household, we compare the household’s access speed to its WiFi speed over time and count the number of times that WiFi speed falls below access speed. For example, if a household has 100 measurements of WiFi and access speeds and, in 40 of 100 measurements, WiFi speed is below access speed, then the bottleneck prevalence for this household is 0.4 (40/100).</p> <p>In our data, 41 of 47 households, or 89 percent, experienced at least one WiFi bottleneck during the period of analysis—that is, a prevalence greater than 0. Thus, we find that WiFi bottlenecks are a common occurrence across households.</p> <p>However, some households experience WiFi bottlenecks more often than others. Approximately half (22) of the households in our sample experience a WiFi bottleneck in 80 percent or more of their measurements and over a quarter (13) of the households experience a WiFi bottleneck in 100 percent of their measurements. Conversely, 16 households experience a WiFi bottleneck in 20 percent or less of their measurements.</p> <p>What explains this difference? Access speed. Among households that experience frequent bottlenecks (80 percent or more), the median access speed is 686 Mbps, whereas it is only 57 Mbps for households that rarely experience bottlenecks (20 percent or less).</p> <p>WiFi bottlenecks are increasingly more prevalent as access speeds increase. Indeed, at access speeds above 400 Mbps, there are very few measurements where WiFi speed exceeds access speed.</p> <h2 id="how-large-are-wifi-bottlenecks">How Large Are WiFi Bottlenecks?</h2> <p>We care not only about the prevalence of WiFi bottlenecks but also about the size of the bottlenecks. If the WiFi speed is performing at 90% of the access speed, it is not significantly impeding the performance of a home’s Internet connection. However, if the WiFi speed is 50% of the access speed, then the household is underutilizing a large portion of the Internet service for which it pays when connecting through WiFi.</p> <p>To evaluate the magnitude of a WiFi bottleneck, we compare the median WiFi speed, access speed, and “actual” speed of households across speed tiers. Here, we use “actual” speed to indicate the real speed at which a household accesses the Internet.</p> <p>The actual speed is equal to the lower of either the median WiFi speed or the median access speed for a given household for a given measurement. For example, if in measurement A, the household’s median access speed is 400 Mbps and its median WiFi speed is 800 Mbps, then the household’s actual speed is 400 Mbps. Conversely, if, in measurement B, the household’s WiFi speed is 200 Mbps and its access speed is 400 Mbps, then the household’s actual speed equals the WiFi speed—that is, 200 Mbps.</p> <p>If WiFi performance is similar to or better than access performance, then the median actual speed should approximately equal the median access speed for each speed tier. We can see that for the first three speed tiers, the actual speed is very close to the access speed. However, these two values begin to diverge in tiers above 200 Mbps. Access speeds continue to increase as we move up in the speed tier, but actual speeds begin to flatten out and approximate the median WiFi speed. That gap between the actual speed and the access speed is due to the presence of WiFi bottlenecks.</p> <p>The size of the difference between the actual speed and the access speed for each tier gives us a sense of the magnitude of the WiFi bottlenecks. For example, households in the 200-400 Mbps tier have a median actual speed of 228 Mbps, while the median access speed is 343 Mbps. This gap indicates that, while paying for access speeds between 200 and 400 Mbps, the median household is typically experiencing actual speeds that are 115 Mbps lower. This gap only increases with higher speed tiers. For households in the 400-800 Mbps tier, the gap between access speed and actual speed grows to 340 Mbps, and for households in the 800 Mbps plus tier to 609 Mbps. That is a lot of purchased speed that is not being used because of WiFi bottlenecks.</p> <h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2> <p>If your WiFi connection is the culprit of your slow Internet, your online experience might not improve merely by upgrading to a higher speed tier. As we have shown in the above analysis, WiFi can be a significant bottleneck at access speeds above 200 Mbps. If you are currently subscribed to a speed tier above 200 Mbps, then a more effective option (and cheaper in the long run) to increase speed performance might be to upgrade your router, purchase a WiFi extender, or relocate your router to a place that enables improved signal coverage.</p> <p>Purchasing a service plan with access speeds of 200 Mbps or higher can make sense if you plan to connect most of your devices to the Internet through wired connections, such as by using an Ethernet cable to link your computer directly to your router or modem. If you plan to use a WiFi network primarily to connect your devices, ask your ISP or consult other resources to identify WiFi equipment that provides speed performance similar to your access speed. Note that the theoretical maximum performance of WiFi equipment might not manifest in real-world settings where household size, building material, and signal interference can result in suboptimal performance.</p> <p>For state and local broadband offices, policies to improve online experience in a community must reckon with the prevalence of WiFi bottlenecks and their effect on lived Internet performance. Although investments in the last mile and middle mile infrastructure are important, they will not significantly improve a community’s online experience if they are not also supplemented with policies to improve the equipment that people use to access the Internet within their homes, such as their WiFi equipment. The analysis above indicates that performance improvements in home WiFi networks are not keeping pace with the improvements in infrastructure. More attention should be given to improving WiFi networks in communities with poor Internet performance.</p> <p><strong>Notes:</strong></p> <ol> <li>Another option is to downgrade the access speed you purchase to match the WiFi speed supported by your wireless network. However, doing so might not decrease your Internet bill depending on your existing service contract with an ISP.</li> </ol> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <p>The analysis for this data story uses speed test measurements collected from our Internet performance measurement devices deployed in Chicago households from October 2021 through September 2022. Specifically, we use Measurement Lab’s Network Diagnostic Tool (NDT7) to measure the download speeds of both the access link (the access speed) and the wireless network (the WiFi speed).</p> <p>Measurements of the access speed for each household are taken approximately once per hour. Measurements of the WiFi speed are more sporadic. To ensure that we are comparing measurements that were taken around the same time, we resample the data for each household using a 6-hour time window and aggregate using the median access and WiFi speed within each window.</p> <p>Due to the limited number of WiFi speed measurements available for some households in our study, we restrict our sample of households to those that had a significant number of WiFi measurements during the analysis period. After resampling the data for each household, we drop households from the analysis that have less than 30 measurements with both WiFi speed and access speed. After dropping such households, our sample consists of 43 households with an average of 226 WiFi and access speed observations per household.</p> <p>For four households in our sample, there is a significant change in the access speed during the period of analysis (most likely due to the household changing their Internet service). To ensure that these changes in the access speed do not affect our analysis, we split the data for these households so that the access speed is constant during the analysis period and treat them as separate households. As a result, we “add” four households to our sample, bringing the total number of households to 47.</p> <p>To create the speed tiers for our analysis, we bin the households in our sample based on the 95th percentile of a household’s access speed. Using this method results in six distinct speed tiers that we use to group households.</p> <p>For more information about the methodology and analysis supporting this data story, refer to the Jupyter Notebook.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="wifi"/><category term="measurement"/><category term="performance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How WiFi bottlenecks affect your Internet experience and what you can do about it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Chicago’s Digital Divide: What Does Census Data Tell Us?</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/chicago-digital-divide-census/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Chicago’s Digital Divide: What Does Census Data Tell Us?"/><published>2022-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/chicago-digital-divide-census</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/chicago-digital-divide-census/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>While disparities in broadband access have received increasing national attention for years, pandemic-induced remote work/school and massive federal broadband investment make questions of internet access particularly salient today. Within Chicago, the city government has recently engaged this issue through programs such as Chicago Connected and Broadband Innovation Zones, as well as launching a Digital Equity Council. Understanding the digital divide is the first step toward its mitigation, enabling the government and policymakers to effectively target the limited resources to the least connected areas.</p> <h2 id="inquiry">Inquiry</h2> <p>To improve understanding of this issue, a Data Science Clinic team and the Data Science Institute partnered with the City of Chicago to quantify the digital divide in the city. Based on input from the City, the team used data from the U.S. Census Bureau to address the following two questions i) What is Internet access (i.e., being able to get online through either a cellular connection or a fixed Internet connection) at a household level across Chicago community areas?, and ii) How does Internet access relate to socioeconomic and population demographics of the community area?</p> <h2 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2> <ul> <li> <p>While roughly 80 percent of Chicago households are connected to the Internet, deep disparities in availability and adoption exist at the neighborhood level.</p> </li> <li> <p>Most disconnected households in Chicago are on the city’s South and West Sides, with up to 40 percent of households lacking Internet in the least connected communities.</p> </li> <li> <p>Low connectivity rates also correlate with factors such as income, race, and unemployment.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="question">Question</h3> <p>Which neighborhoods in Chicago experience the greatest Internet inequity and how do social and economic factors, such as income, race, and unemployment, correlate with Internet availability and adoption?</p> <h2 id="analysis">Analysis</h2> <p>We gathered data from the U.S Census and sorted it into the 77 Chicago community areas (see Methodology for details). Across the entire city, about 21% of households have no internet connection. But when looking deeper within the city at community areas, we observed large disparities in internet access. The areas with the lowest percentage of internet access (percentage of connected households) are located in the South and West sides of Chicago. These include Englewood (57%), West Englewood (57%), Fuller Park (59%), and North Lawndale (60%). By comparison, the areas with the highest access, Lakeview and Near South Side, report access for 91% of households.</p> <h2 id="correlation-between-access-and-population-characteristics">Correlation between Access and Population Characteristics</h2> <p>We then correlated Internet access with the population characteristics of these community areas. We specifically considered the Community Hardship Index, a score calculated by combining six key socioeconomic indicators namely crowded housing, poverty level, unemployment, education, dependency, and per capita income. We found that the community areas with the highest Hardship Scores were more likely to report low Internet access.</p> <p>We further considered associations between internet connectivity and individual factors such as income and race. Community areas with higher median incomes have a positive correlation with greater internet access.</p> <p>Additionally, community areas with a higher percentage of Black or African American populations possess a lower percentage of households with internet access.</p> <h2 id="which-factor-is-most-correlated-with-internet-access">Which Factor Is Most Correlated with Internet Access?</h2> <p>But of all these factors, which are most closely associated with Internet connectivity? We used individual data from the American Community Survey (ACS), also collected by the US Census Bureau, to tease apart the weight of different demographics without the spatial bias of the tract-level data.</p> <p>Our study found that Internet access is most strongly correlated with household income and education. Additionally, households with at least one elderly person are associated with lower Internet access compared to a household with no elderly person. In terms of race, the Black and Hispanic populations are associated with lower Internet access when compared to White and Asian populations.</p> <h2 id="policy-implications">Policy Implications</h2> <p>Our analysis reveals significant disparities in Internet access across community areas in Chicago. Areas with lower Internet access are concentrated on the South and West Sides. These areas have higher poverty and larger minority populations. Policymakers, including the city government, need to take a holistic approach and prioritize their efforts in these most underserved areas.</p> <p>Income is most strongly associated with Internet access, indicating that Internet inequity in Chicago is potentially an affordability issue. Thus, more programs such as Chicago Connected are needed to provide Internet at lower costs. In the longer term, policymakers can also consider facilitating community networks in underserved neighborhoods, bringing down Internet costs as well as providing employment and digital skills to the residents.</p> <p>Finally, we found that Internet access is also associated with education and age, indicating that Internet access might also be limited due to its perceived utility or lack of user-friendliness for certain population demographics. This suggests initiatives are needed to provide educational resources to the community — especially older populations — about Internet use.</p> <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3> <p>Our analysis reveals significant disparities in Internet access across community areas in Chicago. Policymakers should aim investments toward providing affordable Internet services in underserved neighborhoods on the South and West sides of Chicago alongside programs to boost awareness and understanding of Internet usage and adoption.</p> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <p>We use the American Community Survey (ACS) data from the Census Bureau. The ACS data provides annual (and multi-year) estimates of selected social, economic, and housing characteristics of the population for many geographic areas and subpopulations. Each year, the Census surveys around 1 in 38 US households, and the responses are made available to the public.</p> <p>For our analysis, we use the data available at two different granularities. The first kind is the individual survey responses (ACS individual) with coarser geography, i.e., the Public Use Microdata Area (PUMA) code. The second is statistics from survey responses between 2014 and 2019 and aggregated at a Census Tract level. We specifically use the survey question that asks whether the household has access to the Internet. For descriptive analysis of the population characteristics, we also use other variables including race, income, age, etc.</p> <p>We use the ACS tract-level data to quantify access at a community area level. Each community area typically contains multiple tracts. We use a publicly available crosswalk that assigns a tract to one of the 77 community areas. For tracts overlapping multiple areas, the crosswalk assigns the tract to the community area with majority overlap. The tract-level statistics are then aggregated to obtain community area statistics. For descriptive analysis, we use different methods including calculating the Pearson Correlation coefficient and Logistics Regression.</p> <p>We also provide the codebooks for data download and analysis. This can enable us to extend the analysis to other areas in Chicago.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="digital-divide"/><category term="chicago"/><category term="census"/><category term="policy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We evaluate which neighborhoods in Chicago are the least connected in the context of socioeconomic factors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Tale of Two Gigs</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/tale-of-two-gigs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Gigs"/><published>2022-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/tale-of-two-gigs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/tale-of-two-gigs/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By Marc Richardson</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1372368387-1440x580-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1372368387-1440x580-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1372368387-1440x580-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1372368387-1440x580.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>While much attention has been paid to mapping the disparities in availability and adoption of Internet services across communities in the United States, there has been less focus on measuring in Internet performance and user experience. With the development of new datasets containing continuous, granular, and holistic data on Internet performance at the household-level, such as the data collected through the Netrics platform developed here at the University of Chicago, we can begin to ask questions about whether communities that have equal access to the Internet might still experience vastly different performance when online.</p> <h2 id="inquiry">Inquiry</h2> <p>When two people purchase a product or service from the same supplier, they typically expect to receive the same product in terms of quality and experience regardless of where the product or service was purchased. For example, two people purchasing a new 2022 Toyota Camry expect to receive the same car whether they purchase that car in New York City or in Los Angeles. Similarly, two people living in different communities who purchase the same Internet service from the same Internet service provider (ISP) should be able to expect to receive the same performance and reliability from that service. But, do they, in fact, receive the same service?</p> <p>In this data story, we explore whether two households in different neighborhoods in Chicago that subscribe to the same service plan from a given ISP experience comparable performance and reliability when using that service.</p> <h2 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2> <ul> <li> <p>The use of existing datasets on Internet performance to compare the online experiences of different communities is hindered by biases in measurement and sampling. To study disparities in Internet performance across communities, we need continuous, robust measurement of Internet connectivity at the household level.</p> </li> <li> <p>The Internet Innovation Initiative developed a new toolkit and measurement platform, Netrics, that makes it possible to uncover and scrutinize differences in the online experience of households in different communities, opening new avenues for critical research and policy insights into the digital divide.</p> </li> <li> <p>We see different levels of Internet performance for subscribers to the same service in different neighborhoods. This observation motivates the need to study these disparities over time with larger, more carefully constructed samples.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="question">Question</h3> <p>Consider two households on the same plan from the same internet service provider: how much might their experiences differ in terms of performance and reliability?</p> <h2 id="analysis">Analysis</h2> <p>Existing datasets on Internet performance are limited in their ability to reveal inequality in online experiences at the neighborhood level. The data that our Netrics platform collects allows us to start exploring this critical domain of analysis.</p> <p>At the outset, it bears noting that existing datasets on Internet performance cannot easily be employed to study performance disparity across small geographic areas, such as neighborhoods. The sampling techniques of existing datasets do not capture Internet performance in some neighborhoods and cannot say anything about the online experience for those residents. Furthermore, the measurements collected by existing datasets are not continuous and do not represent the “lived experience” of being online within these communities. And, in most cases, the measurements do not capture the true Internet capacity delivered to these communities, due to the influence of other factors such as WiFi performance.</p> <p>The data that our Netrics platform collects overcomes these limitations with continuous, comprehensive measurements of Internet performance at the Internet access point of a household. A comparison of two households subscribed to Xfinity’s gigabit service in different Chicago neighborhoods—Hyde Park and South Shore—reveals a disparity in Internet performance. With Netrics data, we can highlight this disparity both at an aggregate level and overtime for these two households. Although a comparison of two households is clearly far too small to draw general conclusions, the characteristics of the Internet connectivity in these two households highlight the potential of performing such comparisons across neighborhoods.</p> <h2 id="limitations-of-existing-datasets">Limitations of Existing Datasets</h2> <p>Why are existing datasets on Internet performance insufficient for answering the question posed above? To illustrate the challenges with existing datasets, we will use Speedtest Intelligence® data from Ookla® as an example. Our intention here is not to point out the limitations of any particular method or dataset, but rather to illustrate that for any given dataset—specifically data collected with crowdsourcing or convenience samples—there are some limitations to the types of questions that can be answered.</p> <p>Ookla collects performance data when a person runs Ookla’s Speedtest on their computer or mobile device by going to speedtest.net or through Ookla’s Speedtest CLI. As one of our researchers explains in this paper, Ookla’s Speedtests are much more likely to be initiated by people living in wealthy neighborhoods, where Internet infrastructure is less likely to suffer from underinvestment. You can see the blind spots of this kind of “crowdsourced” sampling by looking at a map showing the geographic distribution of the number of Ookla Speedtests initiated in Chicago.</p> <p>In this map, the lighter shaded squares indicate a lack of tests run in conventionally underserved communities in Chicago, such as South Shore. With no data for these neighborhoods, we cannot say anything about the state of internet performance there nor how it compares to other, more well-provisioned areas.</p> <p>Another important limitation of using Ookla data to compare the online experiences of households in different neighborhoods stems from the fact that user-initiated tests are typically run when a household is experiencing a technical problem or undergoing network reconfiguration. The resulting measurements from such tests might not accurately reflect the household’s Internet capacity. An analogy would be looking out a window once per day in the evening, seeing it was dark outside, and concluding that it must be dark 24 hours a day. Tests that are crowdsourced, such as Ookla’s data are more likely to suffer from self-selection bias. It can thus be extremely difficult to use these results to draw generalizable conclusions about an ISP’s performance in a particular area.</p> <p>Furthermore, speed tests initiated from a laptop or a mobile device most likely reflect the performance of a household’s WiFi connectivity, not the fixed service being delivered to the household by the ISP. Many people connect to the Internet wirelessly, over a WiFi network, in their home (as opposed to connecting their devices directly via a cable to the source of the Internet service in their home). Our own past research has demonstrated that as Internet access speeds increase, the user’s home WiFi network is the performance bottleneck.</p> <p>If a household’s WiFi speed is lower than the speed of the fixed Internet connection servicing the house, then the speed test measurement will paint a distorted picture of a household’s Internet performance.</p> <p>In short, existing datasets like Ookla are limited by unrepresentative sampling, infrequent and non-continuous measurement of a household’s Internet connection, and measurement of a household’s WiFi connection, not the fixed Internet connection provisioned for the premise.</p> <h2 id="netrics-continuous-internet-measurement-at-the-household-level">Netrics: Continuous Internet Measurement at the Household Level</h2> <p>Unlike existing datasets, the Netrics platform continuously collects fine-grained Internet performance measurements at the household’s access network, which makes it possible to compare the online experiences of two households in different communities across time.</p> <p>Beginning in early 2021, the Internet Innovation Initiative team began deploying Netrics measurements devices, with a particular focus on deploying devices in historically under-represented neighborhoods such as South Shore.</p> <p>To highlight the potential of the sort of data that Netrics collects, let’s dig deeper into the data and compare the online experience of two specific households located in different neighborhoods, but which subscribe to the same ISP service.</p> <h3 id="two-households-same-internet-service-two-different-online-experiences">Two Households, Same Internet Service, Two Different Online Experiences</h3> <p>From July through August 2021, we deployed our Netrics devices to measure Internet performance in a house in Hyde Park, where the University of Chicago is located, and one in South Shore. Both households were paying for Gigabit Internet service from Xfinity (Comcast).</p> <p>During those two months, we measured each household’s Internet performance using standard network measurement tools. We found that the Hyde Park household experienced higher-quality Internet than the South Shore household.</p> <p>There are many metrics that one can collect to evaluate the quality of an Internet connection. One metric that receives a lot of attention is the rate at which the connection can download and upload data from and to the Internet. This metric is often referred to as Internet bandwidth or Internet speed. Intuitively, the higher the speed of a connection, the faster it can receive and send information and thus the better it performs. From July 2021 through August 2021, the Hyde Park household consistently clocked Internet speeds approximately 100 Mbps higher than the South Shore household.</p> <p>Being able to measure speed continuously is important because if we were to compare the speeds of each household at certain points in time in the chart above, we might conclude that the Hyde Park household experienced lower speeds than the South Shore household. Over time, however, we can see that the trend in speeds experienced by each household is persistently different.</p> <p>Another important metric that is often overlooked is the latency of an Internet connection. Latency is the amount of time, typically measured in microseconds, that it takes to send data to a given website on the Internet (for example, www.google.com) and receive a response back from the website. Latency is critical for video-intensive applications, such as Zoom, and online gaming. Lower latency enables better application quality. If you have ever had a Zoom call where you experienced lag or frozen video, high latency is most likely the culprit.</p> <p>Once again, we can see a significant, persistent disparity in latency between the Hyde Park and South Shore households from July 2021 through August 2021, with the Hyde Park household experiencing lower latency over time than the South Shore household. Working latency, or latency under load, measures latency under conditions in which you typically use your Internet connection when multiple applications and devices are competing for the available bandwidth of the connection. This measurement gives a more realistic picture of the latency you experience online relative to a traditional latency test, which measures latency within a vacuum where no other demand is placed on the network.</p> <p>If we look at the aggregate measurements for each household over this two-month period, we see a disparity across a range of performance measurements.</p> <h3 id="why-does-the-performance-differ">Why Does the Performance Differ?</h3> <p>Unfortunately, there isn’t a simple answer to why we see these differences. The Internet is a vast infrastructure and, as such, there are many factors that can influence the performance experienced by a single household.</p> <p>The quality of the equipment that the household uses to access the Internet, such as the router or the modem, can have a significant influence, with older routers and modems often incapable of supporting the high access speeds of modern networks. The type of technology that the ISP uses to connect the households to the Internet can also have a big effect; if fiber is what connects the household, as opposed to copper wires or coax cables, then performance will typically benefit. Thus, with only two households to compare, it is difficult to draw generalizable conclusions about the state of the Internet in Hyde Park relative to South Shore from this case study.</p> <p>However, with tools like our Netrics platform and sufficient coverage of households, critical questions about performance equality across communities can benefit tremendously from continuous, fine-grained data on Internet performance. To achieve a state of digital equity where communities not only have equal availability of the Internet but also experience comparable quality online, we need to prioritize the use of tools like Netrics. They will no doubt prove to be a valuable source of insight for further understanding what contributes to the disparity in online experiences that we anecdotally know to be true.</p> <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3> <p>With continuous, fine-grained data that the Netrics platform collects, we can begin to scrutinize the disparity in online experience that hinders true digital equity in our societies. The tale of two gigs is a cautionary one; even if we can achieve equity in availability and adoption, we will still be left to ensure that the Internet is empowering communities with equal opportunity and connectivity for all.</p> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <h3 id="netrics-internet-performance-measurement-devices">Netrics Internet Performance Measurement Devices</h3> <p>Netrics measurement devices are connected directly to a home’s source of internet and run multiple tests per day of the Internet connection. Such continuous, granular data provides a holistic view of a household’s internet performance, including metrics on everything from how fast the Internet connection is to how many devices are using the connection at any given time.</p> <p>As of May 2022, Netrics devices are deployed through our Internet study. Enrolled participants install the devices on their home networks. Once the device is installed, it runs network measurements on a pre-determined schedule. Test schedules vary in frequency by measurement. For example, ping latency to various domains is measured approximately every five minutes whereas speed tests are run approximately once every hour. Tests are scheduled to ensure that test runs do not interfere with the results of another test.</p> <p>In the analysis above, we display measurements from the devices for the following:</p> <h4 id="speed-tests">Speed Tests</h4> <p>A household’s wired Internet upload and download bandwidth in megabits per second (Mbps). Internet bandwidth is a measure of how fast your Internet connection is. The more bandwidth that your Internet connection has, the more information it can handle at any given time and the faster it can send that information. We measure Internet bandwidth using three popular tools—Ookla, NDT7, and iPerf3.</p> <h4 id="ping-latency">Ping Latency</h4> <p>The latency to a set of popular websites and geographically distributed servers. Standard network latency is a measure of how long it takes (typically in milliseconds) to send information to a destination on the network and receive a response in return. The ping latency is a standard measurement of latency. We collect ping latency data for:</p> <ul> <li>www.google.com</li> <li>www.amazon.com</li> <li>www.youtube.com</li> <li>www.facebook.com</li> <li>www.wikipedia.com</li> <li>www.chicagotribune.com</li> <li>www.suntimes.com</li> <li>Other servers (University of Chicago, last mile, Measurement Lab test servers in Washington, DC, Atlanta, and Denver)</li> </ul> <h4 id="dns-latency">DNS Latency</h4> <p>The latency to resolve Domain Name Service (DNS) queries to a set of popular websites using Cloudflare’s public DNS resolver, 8.8.8.8. When you visit a website on the Internet (for example, www.google.com), the domain name, “www.google.com”, needs to be matched to an actual IP address before the network can know where to send your information over the Internet. You can think of a website’s IP address as its mailing address, similar to the address of your house or apartment. The domain name “www.google.com” is a nice, human-readable moniker for the actual IP address where Google’s servers are located. It takes time to look up and “resolve” a web domain name, which is what DNS latency measures—the amount of time in milliseconds that it takes to resolve a domain name into an IP address.</p> <h4 id="latency-under-load">Latency Under Load</h4> <p>The average latency under load using both TCP and ICMP pings. Latency under load (or working latency) is another way to measure ping latency, but under network conditions that more accurately reflect the context in which you use the Internet. Typically, the average person does not use the Internet within a vacuum, which is the context in which latency is most commonly measured. Rather, there are usually multiple applications, devices, etc. generating network traffic and competing for available network bandwidth at any given moment you spend online. Latency under load measures latency under those kinds of network conditions, thus supplying a more realistic measure of latency than is given by traditional latency measures.</p> <h4 id="lan-bandwidth">LAN Bandwidth</h4> <p>The local network area (LAN) bandwidth in megabits per second (Mbps). We measure LAN bandwidth by conducting a speed test (Measurement Lab’s NDT7 test) between a participant’s device (laptop) and the Netrics device installed in their residence. This measurement allows us the test the capacity (or performance) of a household’s WiFi network, which can then be compared to the capacity of the same household’s wired Internet connection to determine whether WiFi serves as a performance bottleneck. This kind of measurement can also be useful for understanding WiFi coverage throughout your home.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="measurement"/><category term="netrics"/><category term="chicago"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We compare the Internet performance of two households in different neighborhoods that subscribe to the same Internet service offering.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Integrated Map of Internet Access</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/integrated-map-internet-access/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Integrated Map of Internet Access"/><published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/integrated-map-internet-access</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/integrated-map-internet-access/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By James Saxon, University of Chicago</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/integrated-map-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/integrated-map-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/integrated-map-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/integrated-map.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>A little over a year ago, I created an interactive map of indicators of Internet access, in the twenty largest American cities. In the time since, a number of additional maps have come out, supplementing the FCCs’ maps. Although many are nice, I felt that I could make a modestly cleaner one.</p> <p><strong>FCC 477:</strong> is limited to the 477 data itself (of course!), and is not so easy to navigate. The FCC also has an LTE map that is pretty nice.</p> <p><strong>Illinois Broadband:</strong> is limited to Illinois!</p> <p><strong>NTIA Broadband Map:</strong> has a limited number of variables. Cartographically, it is very hard to read, since all layers can be overlaid, and all are the same color.</p> <p>The other big thing missing from these maps is that the data are not approachable. The raw FCC data are around 10 GB, which is a lot for most people, and filtering them usefully is a pain. The other maps didn’t have a simple, tract-level download, to get people started. I wanted to provide that. You can also find the code that generates those data in this GitHub repo.</p> <p>The map should also still include what I view as the three most-important available data sources on broadband:</p> <ol> <li>The Census’s indicators of both broadband and computer access, and other demographics.</li> <li>The FCC’s 477 reports, aggregated in useful ways: fiber availability, number of ISPs, etc.</li> <li>Ookla’s Speedtest performance data. These need to be reaggregated from quad tiles to Census tracts.</li> </ol> <p>Here is my map:</p> <p>Naturally, it is made using Mapbox, because that is where I will work by the time you read this post. Therefore, it has beautiful vector layers and it is responsive. If you click to go full screen, hovering will also show you the values of observations.</p> <p>The data include a lot of useful broadband variables, all packed up and aligned. In just 4.2 MB, you get every Census tract in the US. From the Census:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">population</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">households</code>: tract population and number of households.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">geoid</code>: Census tract GEOID.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f_broadband</code>: fraction of households with broadband access.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f_computer</code>: fraction of households with a computer.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f_ba</code>: fraction of the adult population that holds a bachelor’s degree.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f_black</code>: fraction of the population that is Black.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f_hispanic</code>: fraction of the population that is Hispanic.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mhi</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">log_mhi</code>: tract median household income, and its logarithm.</li> </ul> <p>From the FCC:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n_isp</code>: the number of Consumer ISPs.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n_dn10</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n_dn100</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n_dn250</code>: the number of ISPs at 10, 100, and 250 Mbps.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">n_fiber_100u</code>: the number of fiber ISPs with at least 100 Mbps in the upstream direction.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fiber_100u_exists</code>: the fraction of blocks in the tract where the FCC believes fiber is available.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">max_dn</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">max_up</code>: the maximum download and upload speeds, reported to the FCC.</li> </ul> <p>From Ookla:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">d_mbps</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">u_mbps</code>: average download and upload speeds observed by Ookla on fixed-line connections (reaggregated from quad tiles).</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lat_ms</code>: average latency observed on Ookla Speedtests.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tests</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">devices</code>: number of Ookla Speedtest measurements, and number of unique devices.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tests_per_cap</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">devices_per_cap</code>: the number of tests or devices, divided by the tract population.</li> </ul> <p>Happy analyzing!</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="broadband"/><category term="mapping"/><category term="data"/><category term="visualization"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read how we built the national map featured on the portal.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Internet Access and Broadband Analysis</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/internet-access-scorecard/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Internet Access and Broadband Analysis"/><published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/internet-access-scorecard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2022/internet-access-scorecard/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By James Saxon, University of Chicago</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/iStock-1028077888-1440x580.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>With support from data.org, we are working to better measure the performance of Internet in American cities. Along with our technical work to develop measurement infrastructures, we want to highlight already-available public data, make them comprehensible, and help others to use them.</p> <p>In this post, I present a “scorecard” of Internet access, for the twenty largest metro regions in the United States. By access, I mean the share of people have broadband Internet. This analysis uses data from US Census Bureau’s American Community Survey and the National Telecommunication and Information Administration (NTIA) Internet performance supplement to the Current Population Survey. Still, this post is more about data than policy. I am providing code, to invite others into the discussion.</p> <p>I rank metro regions by:</p> <ol> <li>share of households that are connected</li> <li>differences in connection rates by race, ethnicity, and gender</li> <li>same as (2), but controlling for income and age levels.</li> </ol> <p>Most of this will focus on the ACS data. At the end, I will delve into the consistency of the ACS with the CPS.</p> <h2 id="access">Access</h2> <p>The first question is: in which cities are broadband subscription rates highest? With a single API call, you can get the populations and broadband subscription rates for every Census “place” or Metro area in the US, from the American Community Survey. That is super easy, and we can retrieve analogous estimates for any geography in the US: states, counties, Census tracts, congressional districts, etc. Using these calls, we see that for either cities or metro regions, Seattle tops out the list. The list for metro regions is above.</p> <p>But we already have an important subtlety to address: how to define cities? Census places or “cities” are jurisdictions. Metro regions are a functional description of how we actually live. Our choice of geography to examine will affect the answers we get. The share of households without broadband is modestly higher in cities than metro regions: 14.9% of households in New York City don’t have home broadband, but that number falls to 12.2% in the metro region. Because poverty is usually higher in cities, this effect appears in most regions. For instance, Philly dips from 15.8% to 11.0% and the numbers in Chicago fall from 16.4% to 12.3%.</p> <p>Cities are boundaries by which a “we” both living and dead has agreed to divvy up, or segregate, America: what representation and tax burdens we accept or refuse to share. If we want to “blame” someone for poor performance, we can use “Census place” numbers to point fingers at the mayor’s office. But doing this, while partially appropriate in a democracy, would understate the digital divide: it is often starker than the place-based numbers indicate. The people who can afford to live outside the city limits and choose to do so are more likely to be online.</p> <p>In this post, I’ll focus on estimates for metro regions. But the reason is as much technical and practical as conceptual (the notion of responsibility, above). The technical reason is that the Census does not release “microdata” (individual responses) for individual cities, but it does release them for metro areas. We have no choice about the geography.</p> <h2 id="who-gets-access">Who Gets Access?</h2> <h3 id="absolute-differences-between-groups">Absolute Differences Between Groups</h3> <p>Our next question is: who gets access, and who doesn’t? Although the Census API does break down broadband estimates by age, income, and educational attainment (in very broad categories) it does not do this for race, ethnicity, or gender. These are the categories we’ll examine here.</p> <p>Doing so requires us to use Public Use Microdata Samples (PUMS) from the Census. PUMS are the individual responses from that people gave to the American Community Survey. They are also now accessible through an API, but while that API does include race as a queryable variable, and can tabulate results for us, it does not include any geography finer than state. (Example tabulation for Illinois.)</p> <p>We can download the full data from Integrated Public Use Microdata Samples (IPUMS) service at the University of Minnesota. Accounts and data are free but the license requires you to download your own data extract. To make progress, we’ll also have to write some code: this is wrapped up in this repo.</p> <p>The second set of columns above thus show the difference in the shares of people with broadband access, in each Metro region, between three groups:</p> <ul> <li>Black and non-Black respondents</li> <li>Hispanic and non-Hispanic respondents, and</li> <li>Women and men</li> </ul> <p>The numbers quoted are, simply, the differences in the (sample-weighted) probabilities that respondents of different groups do or don’t have access. But again, we have a theoretical question. If we want the difference between Hispanic and non-Hispanic access, the numbers are correct. But this encompasses a number of differences. For instance, the Hispanic population is younger and lower income. Ages and income levels unsurpringly explain the vast majority of variation between neighborohoods’ broadband subscription rates. So we could pose a different question: are a Black respondent and a White respondent of the same age and income equally likely to be online?</p> <h3 id="conditional-estimates">Conditional Estimates</h3> <p>There are many ways of addressing this question, but what I’ll do here is called a k-nearest neighbors regression. What this means is that for every respondent in group A (Black, Hispanic, or Female) in a metro area we’ll find the k respondents that are most like them in group B (non-Black, non-Hispanic, or Male), in the same metro. We’ll take the average across the k matched “neighbors,” and compare the response that the respondent actually gave, regarding their Internet access. Again, this answers the question: “if I, a member of group A held constant certain characteristics about myself like age and income but were in group B, would I be more or less likely to have Internet access?”</p> <h2 id="consistency-of-the-acs-and-the-cps-technical">Consistency of the ACS and the CPS (Technical!)</h2> <p>In our work, we were careful to reproduce official estimates before proceeding to the ones that we’ve shared above.</p> <p>The ACS API variable that we used was DP02_0153PE, which is the share of total households “with a broadband Internet subscription.” Note first that this does not include “group quarters” like jails or dorms. But second, while working with the IPUMS data, I found that it was not the broadband variable CIHISPEED but CINETHH that reproduced the API estimates at the state level. CIHISPEED is based on the questionnaire text:</p> <blockquote> <p>Do you or any member of this household have access to the Internet using a broadband (high speed) Internet service such as cable, fiber optic, or DSL service installed in this household?</p> </blockquote> <p>whereas CINETHH is supposed to be any Internet connection:</p> <blockquote> <p>Do you or any member of this household have access to the internet?</p> <ul> <li>Yes, by paying a cell phone company or Internet service provider</li> <li>Yes, without paying a cell phone company of Internet service provider</li> <li>No access to the Internet at this house, apartment, or mobile home</li> </ul> </blockquote> <p>At the state level, the correlation between the API and my reconstructed value was 0.998 with CINETHH but just 0.892 with CIHISPEED. To my mind, this appears to be a data error or a labelling error in the API.</p> <h3 id="the-current-population-survey">The Current Population Survey</h3> <p>The analysis above is based entirely on the ACS data, but the CPS provides similar reports. An analysis using those data is also included in the git repo.</p> <p>Their corresponding survey question is HEINHOME:</p> <blockquote> <p>Does anyone in this household, including you, use the Internet at home? This includes accessing the Internet with a cell phone, computer, tablet, or other device.</p> </blockquote> <p>They also have HEHOMTE1:</p> <blockquote> <p>I am going to read a list of ways that people access the Internet from their homes, other than a mobile data plan. At home, (do you/does anyone in this household) access the Internet using: High-speed Internet service installed at home, such as cable, DSL, or fiber optic service […]</p> </blockquote> <p>So HEINHOME seems to match CINETHH, and HEMOMTE matches CIHISPEED.</p> <p>As above, before proceeding to my own estimates, I paintstakingly reproduced the ones that Rafi Goldberg made for the NTIA’s state-level map.</p> <p>Based on this, the values that we want to compare are HEINHOME in the CPS and the (apparently actually) CINETHH from the ACS’s API. Of course, we must also be consistent between units of observations (households vs person-level), and in the decision of whether or not to include group quarters. Here, I am matching the ACS choices: focusing any access, in non-GQ households. The consistency between the ACS and the CPS was, on the whole, not great. For CBSA’s the correlation between the two measures (ACS broadband via the API and the CPS’s HEINHOME) was just 0.42. For states, the correlation from the ACS API value to HEHOMTE1 was 0.72 (with the Universe described) but just 0.54 for HEINHOME. Numerically, the ACS values are much higher than the CPS ones.</p> <p>One last note: Despite its smaller sample size, the CPS does make it possible to identify the largest twenty cities (Census places) in the United States. This is because they do not also have the smaller “PUMA” geographies that the ACS reports in its microdata. Based on this, I reproduced the population for the twenty largest cities. I was very surprised, and frankly still incredulous, to find San Francisco near the bottom of the heap for pretty much any definition of Internet access. San Jose was at the top. But the differences were also not small!! The NTIA analysts suggest that it might simply be an unusual statistical noise, but that seems unlikely. For certain estimates, San Francisco was 3σ below the rest of California (about a 1 in 300 chance).</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="broadband"/><category term="policy"/><category term="analysis"/><category term="data"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A scorecard of Internet access for the twenty largest metro regions in the United States.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Practical Steps for Improving Your Wi-Fi</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2021/practical-wifi-steps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Practical Steps for Improving Your Wi-Fi"/><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2021/practical-wifi-steps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2021/practical-wifi-steps/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By James Saxon, University of Chicago</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/wifi-steps-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/wifi-steps-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/wifi-steps-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/wifi-steps.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <ol> <li>Place your Wi-Fi far from big hunks of metal and other electronics, <em>especially</em> your microwave.</li> <li>If at all possible, put your Wi-Fi high up, like on a cabinet or a bookshelf.</li> <li>Buy your own modem/router combo.</li> </ol> <h2 id="move-the-wi-fi-away-from-metal-and-microwaves">Move the Wi-Fi away from metal and microwaves!</h2> <p>This is probably the most important point. Your Wi-Fi transmits data as electromagnetic waves, and metal can reflect or shield these waves. I used to work on this physics experiment:</p> <p>It is wrapped in metal. All the beautiful, orange copper is called a Faraday cage. The purpose of this metal wrapping is to block electromagnetic radiation from interfering with the sensitive electronics inside. Simply put, metal blocks electromagnetic waves.</p> <p>This is where I used to have my Wi-Fi:</p> <p>I had it there because that is where the cable came out of the wall, and about as far as it reached. But, in this location, my Wi-Fi access point was nearly engulfed in sheets and chunks of signal-blocking metal: the dishwasher, the oven, and the radiator! It wasn’t quite a Faraday cage, but it was still unwise, and it certainly blocked the signal. Get smart! Move your Wi-Fi away from metal!</p> <p>So why is your microwave oven particularly bad? Your Wi-Fi communicates by emitting and receiving microwaves. The FCC lets Wi-Fi use two frequencies or bands: 2.4 GHz and 5 GHz. Two bands – more data! But the bands also serve different purposes.</p> <p>Lower frequencies are better at penetrating through stuff (walls, furniture, or people), but you can embed more data in higher frequencies. More data means faster “speeds.” So: 5 GHZ is good for speed while 2.4 GHz is good for coverage. Unfortunately, microwaves and old, cordless phones can also use that 2.4 GHz band. When they do, they interfere with the Wi-Fi’s signals.</p> <p>What is the meaning of all this? Well there are two thick, brick walls between the Wi-Fi in my kitchen and the back bedroom of my apartment. When I connect to the Wi-Fi from the bedroom, my computer sensibly chooses the 2.4 GHz band since the signal from that lower-frequency signal is stronger there. Then, around 11am or noon as my neighbors start microwaving food (COVID, so we’re all home), there is a ton of interference on that band. My computer switches over to 5 GHz, but that signal can’t make it through the walls. So my signal stinks.</p> <p>Do I actually see “lunch-time blues?” Yes, yes I do.</p> <p>What’s to be done? If you can’t move your Wi-Fi out of the kitchen, another reliable solution (if it’s possible in your home), is to route an Ethernet cable to spaces in your home where you need high bandwidth, like your home office or 4K streaming device. If that’s not possible, you can look into signal repeaters or mesh networks – but I won’t get into those here.</p> <h2 id="raise-your-wi-fi-to-the-sky">Raise your Wi-Fi to the sky!</h2> <p>The stuff in your apartment is probably on the floor, because well, gravity. If your Wi-Fi access point is on the floor (as mine was), the signals will likely have to go through or around that stuff, to reach you. If your Wi-Fi is up high, the signal can travel through less stuff. The signal will be stronger when it reaches you if it travels through less stuff en route.</p> <h2 id="buy-your-own-equipment">Buy your own equipment!</h2> <p>This tip is a little bit more complicated, but it can potentially save you a ton of money.</p> <p>Out of convenience, most people rent a modem/router/Wi-Fi combo from their Internet Service Provider (ISP). I certainly used to. And in some respects, it simplifies things: one less thing to worry about, one less decision to make. But Comcast charges $14 a month for rentals – $168 a year. For just a little more money, you can buy yourself a better modem/Wi-Fi combo that you will own for years.</p> <p>This saves you money not only on the rental itself; it also makes it easier to maintain a cheaper contract with the ISP. When the “initial rate” of an ISP contract expires, usually after 12 months, you can simply call and tell the ISP to either reset your rate or cancel your contract. Since you own the equipment, there’s nothing to return and no hassle. Then, have your spouse, partner, or housemate sign up for service again at the same address (or do it for them). Three times in the last few years, Comcast just gave me (or my in-laws) the service price I asked for. Once, I had to create a new contract in the “other” spouse’s name. But there was never an interruption in service. By owning my modem, I pay just $25 a month for our home Internet, and it is entirely adequate. My annual gab-fest with Comcast customer service, always performed with a glass of wine, takes about an hour but has saved me up to $500 per year. Owning equipment makes the call a lot easier.</p> <p>If you do decide to replace the ISP rental, there are a few things that you need to be aware of.</p> <p>You need not just a modem or a router, but a modem, router, and Wi-Fi access point. You can read about these distinct functions here. This said, you can easily buy a box that combines these three separate functions.</p> <p>Whatever combo (or set of boxes) you buy, make sure that all components can support speeds well in excess of your current contract. For example, modem, router, and Wi-Fi are rated for 600 Mpbs, 1000 Mbps, and 1300 Mbps, respectively. My contract is 60 Mbps, so these devices are more than capable for me, but if you have a gigabit (1000 Megabit) plan, you’ll need fancier equipment. Moreover, ISPs do tend to bump up speeds over time, and you won’t save yourself any money if you end up buying another router next year. If you rent, Comcast and AT&amp;T do ensure that the device is adequate for your contract. If you buy, you become responsible for that check.</p> <p>The choice among available routers can be a little daunting. PC Magazine has a good and up-to-date review of good Wi-Fi routers for 2021, but these will also require a separate modem. If you’re after simplicity, I have recommended this combo from Netgear for speeds up to about half a gigabit per second (500 Mbps). (Again: if you have a top-tier, gigabit Internet plan, you’ll need fancier, more-expensive equipment.) If you’re looking for something snazzy, Ubiquiti makes good equipment with excellent software, but the learning curve may be steeper. Personally, I have been very happy with my R6900P router, also from Netgear, paired with this modem.</p> <p>A little caveat on all this. Comcast or AT&amp;T should ensure that whatever they rent to you is adequate for your subscription. If that were true, then buying your own equipment would save you money but not improve speeds. However, in my own experience, I was able to improve my experience and speeds measured with the equipment I bought.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="wifi"/><category term="tips"/><category term="home-network"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Three tips to improve your home Wi-Fi performance and potentially save money.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can My Wi-Fi Deliver the Internet Speeds I Pay For?</title><link href="https://internetequity.org/blog/2021/wifi-speeds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can My Wi-Fi Deliver the Internet Speeds I Pay For?"/><published>2021-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://internetequity.org/blog/2021/wifi-speeds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://internetequity.org/blog/2021/wifi-speeds/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By James Saxon, University of Chicago</em></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/lan-vs-isp-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/lan-vs-isp-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/lan-vs-isp-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/lan-vs-isp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>With support from data.org, we have assembled and deployed a suite of tests for home Internet performance.</p> <p>One of my favorites is a test of home Wi-Fi bandwidths. In simple terms, our question is: if I buy some Internet speed from Comcast, can I actually get it from my router to my laptop? By sticking a speedtest server on the router and engaging participants to install a browser extension that regularly checks the speed, we can monitor the capacity of the local network. We then compare that capacity with the bandwidth measured from the router out to Ookla Speedtest, on the larger Internet. If your Wi-Fi bandwidth is lower than your bandwidth from the ISP, you can’t get what you’re paying for.</p> <p>On my own home network, with a dinky 60 Mbps connection, this was true fully a quarter of the time over the last two months. My connection tier is the same one Comcast offers through its low-cost Internet Essentials program. Of course, my median Wi-Fi speed of 245 Mbps exceeds what Comcast delivers, and at its best I record over 500 Mbps. But when there are issues, it’s the Wi-Fi.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/netrics-lan.svg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/netrics-lan.svg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Wi-Fi bandwidth on my home network, as measured from my laptops to a raspberry pi wired to the router, as shown above. </div> <p>Looking at participants’ data from across Chicago, the median across households of the median across tests is just 185 Mbps. In other words, the “average” user got less than 200 Mbps, on average. Since many people subscribe to Internet contracts with hundreds of megabits per second in the downstream direction, nearly two-thirds of participants’ ISPs deliver more to their home than their Wi-Fi can deliver to their devices. For a few tips on setting up your Wi-Fi, see my last post.</p> <p>This has important implications, as Congress and the Biden Administration weigh investments in broadband infrastructures through the American Recovery Plan. Personally, I see enormous potential for investment in building-level Wi-Fi infrastructures, especially in city housing authorities. This is essentially what groups like Education Superhighway are already doing. Renting a modem/router combo from an ISP is quite expensive, although it is included in the Internet Essentials program. Installing it requires a real level of expertise. Why not build out the Wi-Fi professionally, and buy fiber “wholesale” for the entire building?</p> <hr/> <p><em>This research is part of the <a href="https://internetequity.org">Internet Innovation Initiative</a> at the University of Chicago.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-story"/><category term="wifi"/><category term="measurement"/><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Research reveals a significant gap between promised and delivered WiFi performance in home networks.]]></summary></entry></feed>